# ENG. JOHN AKUMU, CEM®

### **Personal Details**

Age 33 years
Gender Male
Marital Status Married
Nationality Kenyan
Religion Christian

Languages English & Kiswahili
Address 15418-00100, Nairobi.
Email akumujn@gmail.com
Mobile No. (+254) 723-431991

### **Career Objective**

To contribute my knowledge, skill and experience in Engineering related fields with a particular emphasis on project design, infrastructure development and management, environmental and energy management, renewable energy, leadership and investment. To apply these in an environment in which these skills are valued and valuable. To have and to create opportunities to improve and broaden my skill set to ensure that I continue to be an asset to my colleagues and the organization.

### **Professional Qualifications & Memberships**

- Registered Professional Engineer, Engineers Board of Kenya (EBK).
- Corporate Member of the Institute of Engineers of Kenya (IEK).
- Member of the Association of Energy Engineers (AEE).
- Member of the Association of Energy Professionals Eastern Africa (AEPEA).

### **Professional Licenses:**

- Licensed Electrician (Class A1) by Energy and Petroleum Regulatory Authority (EPRA).
- Licensed Solar PV Technician (Class T3) by Energy and Petroleum Regulatory Authority (EPRA).

### **Education**

2018 – Ongoi	ng: Currently pursuing a Master of Science in Energy Management at the School
	of Engineering, University of Nairobi.
2004-2009	The University of Nairobi; Bachelor of Science (Hons) in Electrical and
	Electronics Engineering.
1999-2002	Kanyawanga High School; Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education (KCSE)
	attained a mean grade of A
1990-1998	Bondo Nyironge Primary School; Kenya Certificate of Primary Education
	(KCPE) Attained a mean grade of 69 points.

## **Work Experience**

### July 2013 to date

Working with the Ministry of Transport, Infrastructure, Public Works, Housing and Urban Development; State Department of Public Works, Headquarters, Nairobi as an Engineer I (Electrical). My job is in Project Development and Management and involve among others:

- Design and documentation of Electrical and Electronics engineering services for government buildings, infrastructure and construction works in liason with architects, other engineers and quantity surveyors. Tender documentation and processing for various new Engineering projects.
- Site inspection and supervision of ongoing works including preparation of progress reports, project management during project implementation to ensure adherence to quality and specifications.
- Processing of interim payments valuation & final account practical completion, handing over & making good defects certificates.
- Testing and Commissioning of electrical engineering projects and services. Maintenance of installed systems and equipment in new buildings and renovations.
- Preparing specifications for equipment to be installed in various projects.
- Project Survey and Audits on adherence to Engineering standards in Construction.
- Energy consumption audit reporting on various new and refurbishment projects. Design and documenting on projects.
- Power supply to heating, ventilation and air conditioning equipment installed in the buildings.
- Generator design and installation works.
- Lifts and Escalators design and installation; Fire safety, detection and protection; Lightning protection; Security and alarm systems.
- Data and Network Communication systems and telephones networks.
- Lighting Design and Installation. Selection of the best fixtures for the different building uses. Design to achieve best lux distribution. Building automation and control systems installation.
- Electrical power supply and distribution. Energy from the utility grid and also renewable sources from Solar PV. Low voltage (LV) systems, distribution boards and switchgear design and installation.
- Power factor correction and power quality assessment.
- Team leadership and teamwork in the various teams at my workplace.

### **July 2012 to June 2013**

Worked with the Ministry of Lands, Housing and Urban Development, Headquarters, Nairobi as an Engineer I (Electrical).

Carried out design process and contract management which included the following:

- Design and documentation of Electrical and Electronics engineering services for government buildings and construction works in other government facilities.
- Design, preparation of BOQs and documentation of electrical engineering in building services.
- Project Survey and Audits on adherence to Engineering standards in Construction.

- Energy consumption audit reporting on various refurbishment projects. Re-design and documenting on refurbishments.
- Supervision and project management of electrical installation works

## May 2010 to June 2012

Worked with the Ministry of Public Works, Headquarters, Nairobi as an Engineer II (Electrical). Carried out design process and contract management which included the following:

- Interpretation of Electrical Engineering drawings.
- Design, preparation of BOQs and documentation of electrical engineering in building services.
- Tender processing procedures and regulations.
- Supervision and project management of electrical installation works
- Processing interim payments valuation & final account

## February to April 2010

Paid Internship in the ICT department of Quick Data BPO, Vision Plaza, Mombasa Road.

## July – September, 2007

Internship program at the Centurions Systems Ltd. Trained on Repair and maintenance of machines; Design of electronic circuits; Networking of computers and IP address configuration; Instrumentation, research and development.

## **Certified Energy Manager Training & Certification:**

Certified Energy Manager, CEM training – I attended the Certified Energy Managers (CEM) course offered by the Association of Energy Engineers, AEE (International) in collaboration with the Association of Energy Professionals of East Africa (AEPEA) at the Strathmore University, Kenya in July 2018. I am a member of the international body of Energy Engineers, AEE (CEMI-95776).

### **Leadership & Management Training:**

- Senior Management Course at the Kenya School of Government, Kabete Campus, Nairobi, (SMC 271/2017).
- Project Development and Management at the Kenya School of Government, Kabete Campus, Nairobi, (PDM 04/2017).

#### **CAD Software Skills:**

- Experienced in the use of Design Software including AutoCAD, Revit Design and ArchiCAD.
- Proficient in the use of project management software; MS Project, MS Excel.

## **Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) Training:**

 October 2017 - Completed a course in Environmental Impact Assessment and Environmental Audit (EIA/EA) at the Kenya School of Government, Kabete Campus. I have a special interest on Environmental Impact Assessment applied to engineering infrastructure and energy projects. I also have a keen interest on renewable energy and energy management for efficiency and profitability.

## **Project Management Training:**

 Project Management Training (PMP®) training – attended the training towards international project management certification by the Project Management Institute (PMI-USA) conducted by Peak Point Consulting Group, Kenya in August 2019

### **Conferences & Seminars Attended:**

- Attended the UNESCO 5<sup>th</sup> Africa Engineering Week; 3<sup>rd</sup> Africa Engineering Conference and 25<sup>th</sup> IEK International Conference held in Mombasa from 17<sup>th</sup> – 21<sup>st</sup> September, 2018.
- Attended the Future Energy East Africa Conference and Expo held at KICC, Nairobi from 12<sup>th</sup> 13<sup>th</sup> September, 2018.
- Attended IQSK Seminar themed: Assuring Excellence in the Construction Industry held in Naivasha from 29<sup>th</sup> 30<sup>th</sup> October, 2015.
- Attended a Seminar on Energy Audit and Design, Installation and Commissioning of Solar PV systems, Mini-grids and Solar water pumping from 19<sup>th</sup> – 20<sup>th</sup> June, 2019.

#### Area of Specialization:

- Electrical and Electronics Engineering (Infrastructure Design, Supervision and Installation)
- Project Management for Construction and Infrastructure Projects
- Energy Management and Audit
- Building Services Project Management (Electrical Engineering Installation works)
- Environmental Impact Assessment and Environmental Audit
- Renewable Energy, Solar PV and Solar Water Heating design and installation.

## **Interests:**

Travelling and Photography.

Training the Youth and Children – Currently a Sunday School Teacher at CITAM Karen.

#### **Referees:**

Eng. Joseph K. Rugano	Eng. F. K. Mbiti
Principal Superintending Engineer (Electrical)	Ag. Chief Engineer (Electrical)
Ministry of Transport, Infrastructure, Housing	Ministry of Transport, Infrastructure, Housing
and Urban Development	and Urban Development
State Department of Public Works	State Department of Public Works
P. O. Box 41191 – 00100, Nairobi	P. O. Box 41191 – 00100, Nairobi
0719-169 978	0721-389406

Arch. Javan Owino	
Chief Superintending Architect,	
Ministry of Transport, Infrastructure, Housing	
and Urban Development	
State Department of Public Works	
P. O. Box 30743 – 00100, Nairobi	
0722-571417	